Register of the Vooruzhennye Sily na IUgie Rossii. Sudnoe otdielenie. Records, 1918-1927
Hoover Institution Archives
Vooruzhennye Sily na IUgie Rossii. Sudnoe otdielenie. Records,
1918-1927
30010
Vooruzhennye Sily na IUge Rossii. Sudnoe otdielenie
9 manuscript boxes 3.75 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, orders, and affidavits, relating to administration of military justice in the Armed Forces of Southern Russia, Russian emigres in Bulgaria, the political situation in Bulgaria, and the composition and distribution of the First Army Corps and the Don Corps
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1930.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Military offenses--Soviet Union; Refugees; Bulgaria; Bulgaria--Politics and government; Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Refugees
Historical Note
This record group, together with the records of the Chief of Supply of the Russian Army (Nachal'nik Snabzheniia Russkoi Armii), were previously accessioned at the Hoover Institution as the F. F. Abramoff collection. Both groups of records at one point were in the possession of General Abramoff, who commanded the Don Army Corps in Bulgaria, but he was not the originator of the records themselves. The records of the Justice Department of the Russian Army and its subordinate agencies were originally assembled by General I. A. Ronzhin, the Chief Prosecutor of the Russian Army and Navy and the principal executive officer of the Department. After General Wrangel's Russian Army evacuated the Crimea in 1920, the Justice Department was ultimately relocated in Bulgaria, where both the First Army Corps, under General Kutepov, and the Don Army Corps, under General Abramoff, were billeted. General Abramoff probably assumed possession of the files of the defunct Justice Department after many of the Russian Army organizations and offices disintegrated in 1926-1927 because of an acute shortage of funds.
The collection consists of a numerical office file, the papers of General Ronzhin, and the records of judicial organs subordinate to the Department. The office file of the Justice Department consists of papers relating to investigations into relatively minor infractions: theft, missing valuables, insubordination, insulting a superior officer etc. The papers of General Ronzhin are more substantive and include reports sent regularly by all Courts of Honor and military prosecutors and investigators. Among his other duties in Bulgaria, General Ronzhin interceded with the Bulgarian Government on behalf of soldiers from the Don and First Army Corps, who suffered considerable harassment from local police authorities. Consequently, there is a large volume of correspondence with the Bulgarian Interior Ministry. Ronzhin also remained in close contact with General Abramoff, and there is much material received by Ronzhin from either Abramoff or his subordinates.
The records of two subordinate judicial organs--namely, the Special Military Investigator at General Headquarters and the Military Justice Commission at the Sevastopol Fortress--are also contained in the collection. Colonel Ukraintsev was the Special Military Investigator and acted on the direct orders of General Ronzhin, who commissioned him to investigate cases of the greatest import: embezzlement, graft, corruption, execution without trial, etc. The Military Justice Commission at the Sevastopol Fortress appears to have been an extraordinary body evolving out of the chaos that accompanied the retreat of General Wrangel's forces into the Crimean peninsula. It dealt with disorders behind the front lines: robbery, banditry, plundering, depredations on civilian property, murder, etc.
Series Description
- Numerical Office File of the Chief Prosecutor of the Russian Army and Navy, 1920-1927. (Box Box No. 1-3.)
  Correspondence, telegrams, lists, tables, charts, reports, memoranda, orders, affidavits, inquiries, certificates, protocols, questionnaires, acts, requests, maps, newspaper clippings, information bulletins, and decrees, arranged in consecutively numbered folders.
- Numerical Office File of the Special Military Investigator at General Headquarters, 1918-1922. (Box Box No. 4-7.)
  Correspondence, reports, lists, tables, telegrams, affidavits, decrees, acts, accounts, certificates, contracts, declarations, summons, requests, protocols, inquiries, memoranda, orders, information sheets, advance accounts, receipts, circulars, and agenda, arranged in consecutively numbered folders.
- Numerical Office File of the Military Justice Commission at the Sevastopol Fortress, 1920. (Box Box No. 7-8.)
  Correspondence, reports, decrees, protocols, transcripts of interrogations, acts, certificates, complaints, affidavits, accounts, declarations, lists, requests, contracts, passport book, newspaper clippings, and memoranda, arranged in consecutively numbered folders.
- Numerical Office File, 1920-1922. (Box Box No. 9.)
  Correspondence, reports, sentences, protocols, information sheets, declarations, orders, telegrams, accounts, inquiries, affidavits, lists, memoranda, declarations, certificates, passports, photos, newspaper clippings, receipts, requests, acts, tables, and diagrams, arranged in consecutively numbered folders.
Container List
- Numerical Office File of the Chief Prosecutor of the Russian Army and Navy, 1920-1927.
  - File No. 1. Correspondence, reports, memoranda, orders, affidavits, and inquiries relating to: 1) an incident involving soldiers of the Kornilov Artillery Division (First Army Corps) and soldiers of the Bulgarian Army in the town of Svishchov; 2) the situation of Russian emigres in Turkey and other countries of the Near East, and the dismantling of the Russian Consulate in Constantinople; 3) an investigation into the activities of I. V. Novitskii, Secretary of the Consular Court in Constantinople; 4) various cases of theft or corruption among the ranks investigated by courts of Honor; 5) irregularities in the administration of funds for repairs to the transport "Dniepr." 1921-1922. (Box 1.)
  - File No. 2. Correspondence, lists, tables, and reports comprising: 1) reports of the Chief Prosecutor of the Russian Military Court in Bulgaria (Lieutenant-Colonel Uiedinov) and the Military Investigators in Bulgaria concerning cases of theft and corruption in the 1st Army Corps, with related correspondence; 2) reports of the Chief Prosecutor of the Russian Military Court in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. Includes letters signed by General P. A. Kuossonsky. 1922.
  - File No. 3. Correspondence, lists, tables, orders, and charts comprising: 1) summaries of petitions to the Commander-in-Chief, by those convicted in a Court of Honor, for pardons or reductions in sentence; 2) requests for information on certain individuals; 3) copies of General Abramov's orders to the Don Corps; 4) requests for financial assistance, the return of confiscated goods, etc. 1920-1922.
  - File No. 4. Correspondence, reports, decrees, memoranda, affidavits, inquiries, orders, directives, tables, accounts, certificates, and telegrams relating to: 1) the publication of photographs depicting starving people in the Volga region in 1922, and the distribution of these photos by the Bulgarian authorities; 2) the hiring of a legal adviser for the Department of Supply; 3) miscellaneous materials relating to the operations of the Courts of Honor, the Justice Department, the Red Cross Hospitals, and the Department of Supply. 1922-1923.
  - File No. 5. Correspondence, reports, lists, tables, inquiries, and protocols comprising documents relevant to cases brought before the Court of Honor and investigated by the Justice Department, organized by case. 1921.
  - File No. 6. Correspondence, reports, affidavits, questionnaires, acts, protocols, and inquiries, comprising documents compiled on cases brought before the Court of Honor and investigated by the Military Investigator at General Headquarters, organized by case. Reports of the Military Investigator to the Chief Prosecutor with relevant enclosures. 1920-1921. (Box 2.)
  - File No. 7. Correspondence, reports, decrees, affidavits comprising reports of the Chief Prosecutors of the Russian Military Courts in Bulgaria and the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes on cases brought before the Courts of Honor in those countries, along with documents relevant to these cases. 1920-1922.
  - File No. 8. Correspondence, orders, reports, telegrams and lists comprising the accumulated files of the Chief Prosecutor of the Military Court of the Kuban Corps. 1920-1921.
  - File No. 9. Correspondence, reports, and orders comprising correspondence with the Military Agents in Greece, Turkey and the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, and also with the Chief of Staff at General Headquarters, relevant to cases brought before the Courts of Honor in those countries, along with relevant documents. Includes orders of the Commander-in-Chief regarding demotions and exclusions from the ranks of individual officers. 1921-1922.
  - File No. 10. Correspondence, reports, decrees, certificates, acts, lists, and telegrams comprising requests of the Chief Prosecutor of the Russian Army and Navy for investigations into reported cases of theft, graft, corruption, etc., along with reports from these investigations and related documents; lists of individuals brought before the Court of Honor, and conclusions of the Court; reports of the Military Investigator at General Headquarters. 1920-1921.
  - File No. 11. Correspondence, certificates, acts, lists, protocols, reports, affidavits and maps relating to the mission of Colonel Popov (Assistant to the Chief Prosecutor) to investigate the theft of valuables from the Petrograd Exchequer in Kattoro (Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes.) 1921.
  - File No. 12. Correspondence, telegrams, reports, protocols, requests, acts, and memoranda relating to cases of arrest and harassment of Russian emigre soldiers by the Bulgarian police, including correspondence with the Ministry of Internal Affairs of the Stambuliiski government (in Bulgarian). 1922. (Box 3.)
  - File No. 13. Correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings, and information bulletins, comprising: 1) reports on the political situation in Bulgaria; 2) copies of the anti-Communist Russian emigre newspaper Russkaia Pravda; 3) information bulletins put out by various army units--the 1st Army Corps, the Don Corps, the Drozdovskii Infantry Regiment, the Alekseevskii Infantry Regiment, the Kuban Corps, and the Union of Russian Officers in Bulgaria; 4) Correspondence between General Abramov and Generals Monkewitz, Kuossousky and Von Lampe. 1925-1927.
  - File No. 14. Reports concerning the political situation in Bulgaria. 1923-1925.
  - File No. 15. Surveys of the Bulgarian Press. 1923.
- Numerical Office File of the Special Military Investigator at General Headquarters, 1918-1922.
  - File No. 1. Correspondence, affidavits, lists, tables, reports, acts, telegrams, accounts, certificates, and printed matter (much of which is in Italian, French or English) concerning the repairs to be done to the transport "Dniepr," the estimated costs of these repairs, mooring of this transport at the Italian port of Taranto for repairs, and reported cases of misuse of funds and illegal activities of the commission entrusted with these repairs. 1919-1920. (Box 4.)
  - File No. 2. Correspondence, reports, acts, lists, telegrams, decrees, affidavits and tables relating to the investigation of illegal use of funds by the commission entrusted with repairs to the transport "Dniepr," and to the complaint registered by Senior Ship's Mechanic Persianov of the "Dniepr" against the head of this commission, Captain Sergieev. 1920.
  - File No. 3. Correspondence, telegrams, reports, contracts, and lists comprising the files of the Chief of the Russian Naval Base at Constantinople (Rear Admiral Shramchenko) relating to the illegal activities of the commission entrusted with repairs to the transport "Dniepr," 1919-1920.
  - File No. 4. Correspondence, reports, lists, affidavits, telegrams, declarations, decrees, summons, requests, and protocols relating to: 1) the murder of Staff-Captain Rykov; 2) the mishandling of funds by Colonel Koval'kov and Second Captain Drashusov, officers commissioned as representatives of the Supply Department of the Volunteer Army to act as paymasters to army officials in Rumania; 3) abuses committed during the procurement of coal for the Government of South Russia, and the transportation of this coal from Constantinople to Sevastopol. 1919-1921.
  - File No. 5. Correspondence, protocols, decrees, reports, lists, and telegrams relating to abuses committed by officials of the Counter-Intelligence Unit of the 13th Infantry Division, the Observation Department, and other officials of the 2nd Army Corps. 1920.
  - File No. 6. Correspondence, decrees, protocols, telegrams, printed matter, reports, and lists relating to abuses committed by officials of the Observation Division of the 2nd Army Corps staff. 1920. (Box 5.)
  - File No. 7. Correspondence, lists, reports, affidavits, inquiries, decrees, protocols, and telegrams relating to abuses committed by officials in the offices of the Commander of the Kertch Garrison, the Commandant of Kertch, and the Counter-Intelligence Unit (bribery, speculation, drunkenness, the sale of arms to Bolshevik sympathizers, etc.). 1920.
  - File No. 8. Correspondence, reports, memoranda, protocols, decrees, lists, tables, orders, information sheets, and printed matter relating to abuses committed by officials in the offices of the Commander of the Kertch Garrison, the Commandant of Kertch, and the Counter-Intelligence Unit (mostly relating to speculation in various foodstuffs). 1920.
  - File No. 9. Correspondence, telegrams, reports, lists, declarations, orders, minutes, decrees, attestations, and protocols relating to abuses committed by officials in the offices of the Commander of the Kertch Garrison, the Commandant of Kertch, and the Counter-Intelligence Unit (mostly relating to speculation in various foodstuffs). 1920. (Box 6.)
  - File No. 10. Correspondence, lists, receipts, accounts, tables reports, acts, and advance accounts relating to the mishandling of funds by Colonel Koval'kov, an officer commissioned by the Supply Department of the Volunteer Army to act as paymaster to army officials and soldiers in Rumania. Includes reports of the Military Agent in Rumania (General Gerua) on this subject. 1918.
  - File No. 11. Advance accounts, accounts, receipts and reports, comprising the accounts of Colonel Koval'kov and Captain Drashusov, plus an account of money received by the Russian Military Mission in Rumania from Colonel Koval'kov. 1918-1919.
  - File No. 12. Correspondence, lists, tables, reports, protocols, decrees, and memoranda relating to the unauthorized shooting of Colonel V. A. Protopopov, an officer in the 2nd Army Corps accused of mishandling funds allocated for the formation of a regiment among the Crimean Tartars, on orders of General Slashchev-Krymskii and Military Official Sharov, two Okhrana officers, without an investigation or trial, 1920-1921; also relating to the affair concerning General Dostovalov, former Chief-of-Staff of the First Army Corps, 1922.
  - File No. 13. Agenda of the Military Investigator (contains lists of and details on cases under investigation). 1919.
  - File No. 14. Account-book (correspondence, receipts, accounts, tables, and memoranda) of the Special Military Investigator, including correspondence with the Chief of Supply at the Sevastopol Fortress, and containing lists of travel expenses. 1920. (Box 7.)
  - File No. 15. Correspondence, decrees, inquiries, protocols, tables, and accounts relating to the theft of money from the office of Barracks No. 49 through the possession of false documents. 1920.
  - File No. 16. Orders, circulars and directives relating to the activities of the Special Military Investigator and the Military-Naval Court imposing specific penalties for certain crimes (deprivation of privileges, pay, etc.), dealing with problems of jurisdiction, outlining duties of judicial officers, etc. 1920.
- Numerical Office File of the Military Justice Commission at the Sevastopol Fortress, 1920.
  - File No. 1. Correspondence, decrees, protocols, transcripts of interrogations, lists, affidavits, and reports related to the theft of money and valuables from a banker in Odessa, Alfred Osipovich Haus, by members of the Odessa Garrison during the evacuation of that city by the Whites (3 vols.). 1920. (Box 7.)
  - File No. 2. Correspondence, protocols, decrees, certificates, requests, passport book, contracts, acts, and reports relating to a series of robberies and murders committed by armed bandits in the Simferopol Region and in other parts of the Crimea. 1920. (Box 8.)
  - File No. 3. Correspondence, decrees, protocols, lists, certificates requests, memoranda, complaints, affidavits, and reports dealing with cases of armed robbery, theft, and property depredations committed against civilians on the Crimean peninsula. 1920.
  - File No. 4. Correspondence, protocols, certificates, accounts, newspaper clippings, declarations, memoranda, affidavits, and reports dealing with several cases of armed robbery, banditry and theft in the vicinity of the Sevastopol Fortress. 1920.
- Numerical Office File, 1920-1922.
  - File No. 1. Correspondence, reports, sentences, protocols, information sheets, declarations, orders, telegrams, accounts, inquiries, affidavits, and lists relating to cases of fraud, theft, missing valuables, false arrest, abusive language, insubordination, etc.: papers relative to inquiries into these matters. Papers are organized by case, labelled, and numbered consecutively, and cases are summarized and listed in a table at the front of the folder. 1920. (Box 9.)
  - File No. 2. Correspondence, reports, inquiries, memoranda, orders, affidavits, instructions, and protocols relating to cases of theft, misconduct, insubordination, disputes between officers, abusive language, agitation on behalf of the Bolsheviks, etc.: papers relative to inquiries into these matters. Papers are organized by case and numbered consecutively. See table at front of file No. 1 for listing. 1920-1921.
  - File No. 3. Correspondence, reports, inquiries, memoranda, declarations, certificates, protocols, passports, photos, lists, tables, and newspaper clippings relating to: 1) the mishandling of funds by Colonel Kostetskii, Assistant to the Commandant of Simferopol; 2) the arrest and detention of two Russian officers by the French authorities in Constantinople. Includes inquiries conducted by the Special Military Investigator on orders of the Chief Prosecutor. 1921.
  - File No. 4. Correspondence, reports, inquiries, protocols, information sheets, diagrams, receipts, requests, affidavits, and acts relating to cases of theft, plundering, negligence in the performance of duty, distribution of Bolshevik propaganda, arson, abusive language, etc. Papers are organized by case and numbered consecutively. See Table at front of File No. 1 for listing. Includes inquiries conducted by the Special Military Investigator (Colonel Ukraintsev) on orders of the Chief Prosecutor, and by Lieutenant Sergieev of the Justice Department. 1921.
  - File No. 5. Orders, correspondence, and reports, comprising orders, extracts from orders, and clarifications of orders issued by the Commander-in-Chief relative to the administration of punishment to officers convicted in a Court of Honor, problems of jurisdiction, the preservation of discipline, and other matters relating to the work of the Justice Department. 1921-1922.